<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Byte&#x27;s Projects</title>
    <link href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects" />
    <updated>2025-11-29T21:31:31-06:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Byte</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Using Linux as my Main OS for the first time</title>
        <author>
            <name>Byte</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/using-linux-as-my-main-os-for-the-first-time/"/>
        <id>https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/using-linux-as-my-main-os-for-the-first-time/</id>

        <updated>2025-11-29T09:09:20-06:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    Ever since August 2024, I've been using Linux as my main OS. Why? Well it's more private, they don't install unnecessary apps like other OS's, and you can customize it as much as you want. Simple. I also like it because lots of servers use&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
  <p>
    Ever since August 2024, I've been using Linux as my main OS. Why? Well it's more private, they don't install unnecessary apps like other OS's, and you can customize it as much as you want. Simple. I also like it because lots of servers use it and in the future if I administer servers, learning linux is good, so far I know alot, package managers, software, fun easter eggs, etc. I like it, I also like something called "LUKS" which is basically a encryption system that encrypts your drive data, I'm not interested in that part, I like the way it stores the encryption key.. Instead of your password being the encryption key, the encryption key is actually a random string from what I know, and THAT string is encrypted with your password, so your password is used to get that encryption key to decrypt your data. But with that.. You can setup multiple "slots" or holders of that encrypted encryption key copy.. Like a security key could hold the same encryption key, and decrypt your data. I find it a creative idea!
  </p>

  <p>
    Also, as I said it's really customizable. I added a notepad widget to my screen, a extension to make my screen more red, and way more that's not included in this screenshot, but here's my desktop.
  </p>

    <figure class="post__image post__image--center">
      <img loading="lazy" src="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/7/Untitled-2025-11-07-1049.png" height="826" width="1452" alt=""  sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/7/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1049-xs.png 640w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/7/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1049-sm.png 768w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/7/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1049-md.png 1024w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/7/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1049-lg.png 1366w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/7/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1049-xl.png 1600w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/7/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1049-2xl.png 1920w">
      
    </figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Networking</title>
        <author>
            <name>Byte</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/networking/"/>
        <id>https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/networking/</id>

        <updated>2025-11-29T08:46:20-06:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    Oh where do I start, I'll just say, theres probably way more than what I mention here to networking since it's such a broad term, but I'll say what I know. Lots of people know the basics, Wifi, Ethernet, "Knowing someone's IP address = I'm&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
  <p>
    Oh where do I start, I'll just say, theres probably way more than what I mention here to networking since it's such a broad term, but I'll say what I know.
  </p>

  <p>
    Lots of people know the basics, Wifi, Ethernet, "Knowing someone's IP address = I'm a super cool hacker" (I'm explaining why that last one is wrong btw)
  </p>

    <h2 id="ip-basics">
      IP Basics
    </h2>

  <p>
    Firstly, lets start with IP's since they found alot of networking from what I know. So, there's two types of IP's. Theres "private IPs" and "public IPs" how they work is when you connect to a Wifi network or connect via ethernet, the router gives your device (phone, laptop, tablet, computer) this magic number called a Private IP, this is used for the router to identify you, and also so other devices can identify you, if your device is also hosting a server (mine has hosted many ;D) then other devices on that same network (example: wifi network) can use the private IP the router assigned you to access that server that your device is hosting. Now, what if you want people outside your (wifi) network to access your server? Well then people will need your Public IP and you'll need to change some router settings.
  </p>

  <p>
    So, you're hosting a minecraft server on your computer and you want your friends to join but they arent on your wifi network? Cool! Here's an explination. First: Go to your router settings, now, this varies by router. Now, go to port forwarding (some call it something else), setup port forwarding (I can't be specific because again it's specific to your router brand and model, but you can usually just google "(your router creator and model) port forwarding tutorial" and you'll see step by step), then run the server on your computer, make sure your firewall allows the connections, and you're done. this applies to any server, not just minecraft. Now, your friends will use (your public IP):(port) to connect.
  </p>

  <p>
    Also, just to reenforce private IP's are network specific, let me make 2 examples. First, technical one. Lets say my private IP the router gave my laptop is 192.168.56.12, well, if my friend on a different wifi network tries connecting to 192.168.56.12, they can't, the router will be confused, unless the router assigned 192.168.56.12 to another device like maybe his phone then he'd be connected to his phone, not my laptop. Here's a real life example, pretty easy to understand. Let's say you have a room, 1st door 2nd floor. If your friend went to his 2nd floor in his house and opened the 1st door, he wouldn't be in your room. Simple.&nbsp;
  </p>

    <h4 id="domains-intro">
      Domains intro
    </h4>

  <p>
    But here's the problem, this is a good setup for a one time event, but what about for a 24/7 server? Well you may be wondering "What's the problem now? I set everything up, it should be ok forever now right?" WRONG. Ok so basically most router's that are for home use, like your or my parent's router change the public IP! I know, shameful. lol. So, how do we deal with that? Well so far my best solution is Domains. What are domains? Welcome to the next chapter.
  </p>

    <h2 id="domains">
      Domains
    </h2>

  <p>
    Domains, you see them everywhere, google.com, example.com, this website right here is on a domain! But what are they? Ever wondered whats happening behind the scenes when you hit enter after typing "google.com" Probably not, I don't blame you honestly. WELL TOO BAD you've read everything before this part already so that means you're interested in what I have to say (thanks!) So, domains have these things called records, there are lots of types of records, to be honest I don't understand many, but most websites use CNAME or A, those basically point to a server from what I know. A points to an IP, I don't really know how CNAME works honestly. So, here's how you would setup a domain for your minecraft server.
  </p>

    <h2 id="minecraft-server-sample">
      Minecraft server sample
    </h2>

  <ol>
    <li>Make sure you setup port forwarding, the minecraft server itself, and your firewall is ready</li><li>Get your Public IP (you can search "what is my ip")</li><li>Go to your domain and make an A record, set the value to the public IP you got</li><li>You're done.</li>
  </ol>

  <p>
    Lets say the domain you got is example.org, and your minecraft server is on port 25565, here's how it would work behind the scenes:
  </p>

  <ol>
    <li>Your friend types example.org:25565</li><li>Your computer looks up the records for example.org</li><li>It finds the A record leading to your public IP (lets say 1.1.1.1)</li><li>It connects to 1.1.1.1:25565</li><li>Your router (1.1.1.1) checks it's port forwarding settings for port 25565</li><li>It see's you made a setting to forward port 25565 to port 25565 on your computer</li><li>Your router connects to <u><em>port</em></u> 25565 on your computer and <em><u>forwards</u></em> all data sent through your friend's computer to yours.</li>
  </ol>

  <p>
    So basically your router is this huge proxy that points connections to the right place.
  </p>

    <h2 id="the-i-know-your-ip-i-own-you-theory">
      The "I know your IP, I own you" theory
    </h2>

  <p>
    Ever been online and seen people threatening each other with their IP's or something, saying they know where the person lives or whatever, yeah thats actually a lie. Firstly, this IP they're talking about is the person's Public IP as we learned previously. Well, your ISP (the people that you pay for internet) has a building somewhere in your city or another city, and that's where your public IP's location is usually. Not your house. Sometimes, if your ISP doesn't have a building in your city, your public IP's location may even be set to the city beside yours because that's the closest building your ISP has.
  </p>

    <h2 id="done">
      Done
    </h2>

  <p>
    I probably know more about networking, right now I just can't think of anything else. Sorry!
  </p>

  <p>
    There's also SSL certificates and that stuff but I think thats a topic for a different time.
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>My first worldwide project (Mumble)</title>
        <author>
            <name>Byte</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-first-worldwide-project-mumble/"/>
        <id>https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-first-worldwide-project-mumble/</id>
        <media:content url="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/Untitled-2025-11-07-1050.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-11-29T08:44:34-06:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/Untitled-2025-11-07-1050.jpg" alt="" />
                    Before I start, I'll just say, this is a huge milestone in my adventures, I am pretty proud of myself for making this work. I woke up one day (yesterday), and as someone who loves open source and self hosting, I decided to run my&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/Untitled-2025-11-07-1050.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                
  <p>
    Before I start, I'll just say, this is a huge milestone in my adventures, I am pretty proud of myself for making this work.
  </p>

  <p>
    I woke up one day (yesterday), and as someone who loves open source and self hosting, I decided to run my own Mumble server, If you don't know what Mumble is, it's basically this server code that you run to make your own voice call server that others can talk on. Now I've run plenty of servers before that are only accessible on my LAN. Simplified, the way networking works (if you wanna know in more detail, read <a href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/networking/">this post</a>) is unless you change some settings on your router, any server your computer runs cannot be seen by the rest of the world, it can only be accessed on people that are on the same network (are connected to the same wifi as you or ethernet or whatever you use to connect) as you. If not, they cannot access it. But, today I decided is the day I make it accessible anywhere. Firstly, I setup the Mumble server itself with <a href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/the-docker-rabbit-hole/">Docker</a>, then I tested it. It works. Now was the hard part, the part I never did before. To those who have done this before, it may seem small, but this was my first time, it was really exciting! So I went into my parents router settings (they don't mind), and looked up how to setup port forwarding on my router model (it was pretty complicated) but eventually it worked! I had to make a "custom service," specify ports, connect it to my computer through some weird UI, but in the end, I did it! I got it so if you connect to port&nbsp;64738 (default mumble port) through my public IP (the magical number the world uses to connect to your servers and router) it routes you to my computer's mumble server! Perfect.
  </p>

    <figure class="post__image post__image--center">
      <img loading="lazy" src="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/Screenshot-from-2025-11-29-08-52-00.png" height="144" width="619" alt=""  sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/responsive/Screenshot-from-2025-11-29-08-52-00-xs.png 640w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/responsive/Screenshot-from-2025-11-29-08-52-00-sm.png 768w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/responsive/Screenshot-from-2025-11-29-08-52-00-md.png 1024w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/responsive/Screenshot-from-2025-11-29-08-52-00-lg.png 1366w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/responsive/Screenshot-from-2025-11-29-08-52-00-xl.png 1600w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/5/responsive/Screenshot-from-2025-11-29-08-52-00-2xl.png 1920w">
      <figcaption>"AONEM" is the nickname I gave for mumble, HTTP was also needed because later on I got a Lets Encrypt certificate for SSL, which was also a big achievement</figcaption>
    </figure>

  <p>
    But now here's another problem.. most home routers change your public IP, that's bad. By the way, this mumble server was just for me and my family to decentralise from corporations and whatnot. So if the public IP changed, my family would need to change it all on their computers too, that would be annoying and a waste of time. So I realized something. You know domains right? Like example.com, or example.org, well, those are kind of aliases for IP addresses, like google.com is pointing to 142.250.191.142 as of the time I'm writing this,&nbsp;142.250.191.142 is google's public IP right now, don't believe me? Go open your browser, and type&nbsp;142.250.191.142 as the URL. Magic right? Nope, just <a href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/networking/">networking</a>&nbsp;basics. So anyway, the thing is.. these aliases can change. So what if instead of asking my family to use the public IP of my router as the address to connect to the Mumble server and have to manually change it everytime my router changes it's public IP, what if instead, I just got a domain, and anytime the public IP changed, I update the IP the domain is pointing to. This is actually a popular concept known as "Dynamic DNS" which from what I understood does exactly what I needed. Well, here's the problem, domains cost money. But, theres a free service that allows you to get free subdomains. So I got all the puzzle peices now! I got a domain, my port forwarding setup, the mumble server works. Now I just need to setup the domain and everything should work, right? Well, you'll find out later. So I made the domain record, setup Dynamic DNS by making a quick script that gets my public IP every 15 minutes, and sends it to the domain, if it changed, the domain forwards to my new public IP, if not, nothing changes. That's basically dynamic DNS, here's my script if you want. I had to censor alot because it includes login credentials and other private stuff.
  </p>
<pre class="line-numbers  language-html"><code>  #!/bin/bash
USERNAME="(secret)"
PASSWORD='(secret)'
DOMAIN="(secret, kinda).privatedns.org"
IP=$(curl -s https://ipv4.icanhazip.com)

curl -k "https://${USERNAME}:${PASSWORD}@(secret)/nic/update?hostname=${DOMAIN}&myip=${IP}"

</code></pre>

  <p>
    Since I'm using linux, I setup something called a "cron" job (that is basically an automated task scheduler) to run this script every 15 minutes. And guess what? It worked. If my public IP ever changes, my family just needs to wait a max of 15 minutes before my computer detects it and the domain is realigned with my router's new IP.
  </p>

  <p>
    Now, an even bigger thing I never done before, get an actual certificate! Certificates, in simple, encrypt your connection with websites, almost every uses them, this blog uses it, Google uses it, as I said, almost every website in the world does, it makes sure nobody except the website can see what you're sending to the website, like your name and password, and it makes sure nobody except you can see what the website sent back, like your bank balance or email address or phone number. Certificates can be made with a "custom CA" but devices only trust a specific list of CAs, so what's a CA, again I'm simplifying this but basically it's a trusted organization that issues these certificates, the most popular one for website certificates is Lets Encrypt, they're trusted very very widely. So, I put my domain into lets encrypt and basically asked them for a certificate, this is necessary because it encrypts the voice communication between the mumble server I made and my family so nobody can eavesdrop. Then they told me I need a http server to prove I own the server, which I also had to setup and port forward. But after a whole bunch of work, I got a certificate, I also decided to setup another cron job to renew the certificate everyday at 3am. That's the story of my Mumble server journey. Hope you learned something!
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Sick of cloud storage fees? Try Nextcloud.</title>
        <author>
            <name>Byte</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/sick-of-cloud-storage-fees-try-nextcloud/"/>
        <id>https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/sick-of-cloud-storage-fees-try-nextcloud/</id>

        <updated>2025-11-29T08:41:41-06:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    If you've been on the internet for a bit of time, you probably heard of cloud storage, I won't say names, but their prices can be very expensive in the long run. Well, there's this thing called Nextcloud, which is run on your systems, meaning&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
  <p>
    If you've been on the internet for a bit of time, you probably heard of cloud storage, I won't say names, but their prices can be very expensive in the long run. Well, there's this thing called Nextcloud, which is run on your systems, meaning you have full control over it, this concept is known as "self-hosting" which means you control your own data and the application is run on your server/computer or multiple if you have a cluster. Anyway Nextcloud does everything most cloud hosts do, it can store your contacts, calendar, files obviously, and people made lots of extensions that let you store way more, like passwords, make forms even, and so on. It also of course supports SSO, so I made sure to integrate <a href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-obsession-with-sso/">Keycloak</a> with it for easy sign in. It also supports WebDAV, which makes alot of modern file managers support transferring files directly from your file manager, I know, awesome!
  </p>

  <p>
    Have fun with Nextcloud.
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The docker rabbit-hole</title>
        <author>
            <name>Byte</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/the-docker-rabbit-hole/"/>
        <id>https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/the-docker-rabbit-hole/</id>

        <updated>2025-11-29T08:38:00-06:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    I've been using docker for a while now, docker compose, I have at least 20 images. Docker is a VERY awesome software for managing servers. I used it to setup my Keycloak&nbsp;systems, I even once made my own docker image that made an API for&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
  <p>
    I've been using docker for a while now, docker compose, I have at least 20 images. Docker is a VERY awesome software for managing servers. I used it to setup my <a href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-obsession-with-sso/">Keycloak</a>&nbsp;systems, I even once made my own docker image that made an API for an app that converted a plaintext token to a JWT because it wouldn't work without one. Making docker images involves a Dockerfile, which is in my opinion its own programming language. Anyway, once I started with docker, I can't leave. I ran a <a href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-first-worldwide-project-mumble/">Mumble server with it</a>, Keycloak as mentioned before, local image converter, text decoder and decryption, <a href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/sick-of-cloud-storage-fees-try-nextcloud/">nextcloud</a>, wireguard, LDAP servers, and even a drawing app (I love you excalidraw)
  </p>

  <p>
    In summary what docker does is basically you run server apps in containers which locks them to only be able to use the files and computer resources and ports you allow it, you're basically locking down a server application into a certain environment
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>My first (kinda) business</title>
        <author>
            <name>Byte</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-first-kinda-business/"/>
        <id>https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-first-kinda-business/</id>

        <updated>2025-11-29T08:27:12-06:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    Back at this time, my parents were always running out of paper towels, I know, specific, but listen. I learned something, whenever they get paper towers, they drive 15 minutes to get some more, then I thought "What if, when we go shopping, I buy&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
  <p>
    Back at this time, my parents were always running out of paper towels, I know, specific, but listen. I learned something, whenever they get paper towers, they drive 15 minutes to get some more, then I thought "What if, when we go shopping, I buy my own paper towels, store them somewhere in my house, then whenever my parents need them, instead of them driving 15 minutes, I sell them with a 'convenience fee' as a charge for saving them 15 minutes of driving" and it worked SOOO well! In 3 months I made $90, then we had to shut it down because we were moving. Of course, I love tech, so I made a LAN inventory tracker, integrated it with a keycloak server for SSO (I love keycloak) and it was a hit! It even sent out receipt emails to my parents via email, heres a screenshot of a email that got sent to my dad when he bought some paper towel once. I also decided to name it AnPlan because I thought it sounds good.
  </p>

    <figure class="post__image post__image--center">
      <img loading="lazy" src="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/2/Untitled-2025-11-07-1048.png" height="900" width="1751" alt="A screenshot of a email sent to my dad confirming his order"  sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/2/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1048-xs.png 640w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/2/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1048-sm.png 768w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/2/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1048-md.png 1024w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/2/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1048-lg.png 1366w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/2/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1048-xl.png 1600w ,https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/media/posts/2/responsive/Untitled-2025-11-07-1048-2xl.png 1920w">
      
    </figure>

  <p>
    My parents liked this idea, especially my Dad, because I learned about how businesses work, they make or buy something, sell it at a higher price, and make profit. So I learned about what would be a fair profit percentage, and how to sell, manage inventory, and integrate with SSO, awesome project in my opinion!
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>I love Keycloak</title>
        <author>
            <name>Byte</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-obsession-with-sso/"/>
        <id>https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-obsession-with-sso/</id>

        <updated>2025-11-29T08:19:42-06:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    Ever since a year ago I've been experimenting with keycloak&nbsp;and oh my it is beautiful! You can setup SAML and OIDC clients so easily, and they even integrate with LDAP and Kerberos. One time I used Keycloak is with my inventory tracker, I had some&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
  <p>
    Ever since a year ago I've been experimenting with <a href="https://keycloak.org" target="_blank">keycloak</a>&nbsp;and oh my it is beautiful!
  </p>

  <p>
    You can setup SAML and OIDC clients so easily, and they even integrate with LDAP and Kerberos. One time I used Keycloak is with my <a href="https://byteafterlife.github.io/projects/my-first-kinda-business/">inventory tracker</a>, I had some other family related apps, and I got them to use Keycloak to sign in with one password into all of them. It made it way more convenient for them. I also of course used it with docker because I was then and still am currently obsessed with docker.
  </p>

  <p>
    Unlike other open source identity providers like OpenLDAP or Authentik or some others like that, Keycloak is easy to use. I just tell you, it took me an hour entering ldap commands into openldap just to get one more attribute into a user, their fingerprint ID for a system I was making, and I still couldn't get it. In keycloak, it was way easier. I just did Realm Settings &gt; User profile &gt; Create attribute, filled in the fields, and I'm done! I also learned how to retrieve those fields in their API, so in my system it queried the API using a "service account" client, it searched for a user based on the fingerprint ID, and found the user's details. In my opinion, if you need a good balance between customizability and simplicity, use Keycloak.
  </p>

  <p>
    Have fun!
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
